Cristina Lois Gómez

Massachusetts Institute of Technology Research Laboratory of Electronics, Room 36-705 77 Massachusetts Ave. Cambridge, MA 02139-4307 (USA)

phone: +1(617)-319-3615 email: clois@mit.edu web: bit.ly/crislois

Summary

9 years of experience in Biomedical Imaging, covering a wide range of topics from detector development to clinical applications. Proven track record of successful management, innovation, and impact in bioengineering. Proven ability to work in a team environment on multi-disciplinary, international projects, as well as independently. Proven communication skills.

Professional Experience

Harvard Medical School & Massachusetts General Hospital

Boston, MA

Research Fellow in Radiology

Jul. 2015-present

- Applied PET/MR imaging to search for markers of disease and progression in Huntington's Disease. This is being used in a clinical trial to test new treatments.
- Worked on multi-modal human neuroimaging to explore and develop new concepts in healthy and diseased brain function.

Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Cambridge, MA

"M+Vision" Research Fellow

Jul. 2012-June 2015

- Intensive training on identifying unmet clinical needs and design solutions with high translational potential and marketability.
- Investigated the biological basis of the placebo effect in depression using PET/MR imaging.
- Worked on the development of a new PET tracer for early assessment of treatment response in melanoma patients. Received a \$283K grant as co-PI to develop this project.

Hospital Clinic Barcelona

Barcelona, Spain

Visiting Researcher

Jan. 2012- Jun. 2012

Evaluated dual-time point PET for prediction of treatment response in lung cancer patients.

Imaging Science Institute

Tübingen, Germany

Visiting Researcher

Feb. 2011- Jul. 2011

Analyzed the effect of MRI contrast agents on PET quantification for PET/MRI applications, and demonstrated how to avoid potential artifacts that could impact clinical decisions.

University of Santiago de Compostela

Santiago de Compostela, Spain

"Angeles Alvariño" Fellow

Dec. 2008-Dec 2011

Designed and built an affordable preclinical SPECT system by reusing a clinical gamma-camera. Recipient of a $60K \in grant$ as PI to carry out the project. Supervised a graduate student.

University of Tennessee Medical Center

Knoxville, TN

Postdoctoral Research Associate

Feb. 2007- Jul. 2008

Demonstrated the benefits of incorporating time-of-flight information in PET/CT by carrying out a study on a large population of 100 oncology patients. Published two highly cited papers, one chosen as cover in *Journal of Nuclear Medicine*.

University of Santiago de Compostela

Santiago de Compostela, Spain

Postdoctoral Research Assistant

Sep. 2006-Jan 2007

Measured the neutron fluency in a linear accelerator to estimate its contribution to the radiation dose in radiotherapy patients.

University of Zürich Zürich, Switzerland

University of Santiago de Compostela

Research & Teaching Assistant

Santiago de Compostela, Spain Sep. 2002–Jun. 2006

Contributed to the design and development, and carried out performance studies of the silicon microstrip detectors installed in the Silicon Tracker of the LHCb experiment at CERN.

Education

PhD in Physics, with European Doctorate University of Santiago de Compostela Oct. 2001 - May 2006 Santiago de Compostela, Spain

MSc in Particle Physics & Non-linear Dynamics

Oct. 2001 - Sep. 2003 Santiago de Compostela, Spain

University of Santiago de Compostela

Oct. 1995 - Sept. 2001

BSc in Physics

University of Santiago de Compostela

Santiago de Compostela, Spain

Leadership service

Chair of the "PET imaging" session at the 2011 IEEE Nuclear Science Symposium and Medical Imaging Conference, Valencia, Spain.

Referee for Medical Physics, Physics in Medicine and Biology, and Zeitschrift für Medizinische Physik.

Management Committee Member to EU COST Action TD1007 for "Bimodal PET-MRI molecular imaging technologies and applications for in vivo monitoring of disease and biological processes".

Reviewer for the Instituto de Salud Carlos III Grants 2015, in the modality of Technological Developments for Health Applications (AES 2015).

Skills

- Imaging techniques: (TOF)-PET/CT, SPECT, and PET/MR.
- Radioactive Facilities Supervisor License, Spanish Nuclear Safety Council, 2009.
- Experience in international, large-scale R&D environments.
- Experience working in multi-disciplinary teams with members from academia, industry, and clinics.
- Principal Investigator in 3 research grants and collaborator in other 11 grants and contracts with industry.
- Authored +60 scientific publications, and delivered +20 invited talks and conference presentations.
- Languages: Native Spanish, Native Galician, good English, and basic German.

Awards

M+Vision Fellowship

Madrid-MIT M+Vision Consortium

Jul. 2012

Ranked 2nd among more than 100 applicants.

"Best Oral Presentation in Nuclear Medicine" Spanish Nuclear Society Annual Meeting

Oct. 2010

Aug. 2009

Front cover of the Journal of Nuclear Medicine, Vol. 50

Featuring results on "Impact of Time-of-Flight on PET Tumor Detection".

José Castillejo Fellowship

Ministerio de Educación y Ciencia, Spain

Sep. 2007–Jun. 2008

Ángeles Alvariño Fellowship

Xunta de Galicia, Spain Dec. 2008–Dec. 2011

Ranked 2nd among more than 200 applicants.

Predoctoral research grant

Universidad de Santiago de Compostela, Spain

Excma. Diputación Provincial de A Coruña, Spain

Excma. Diputación Provincial de A Coruña, Spain

Jul. 2003–Jul. 2004

Jul. 2002–Jul. 2003

Selected Publications

See also my Google Scholar profile at bit.ly/cloispubs.

- P. Aguiar *et al.*, "A portable device for small animal SPECT imaging in clinical gamma-cameras", *JINST* **9** P07004 (2014).
- C. Lois *et al.*, "Effect of MR contrast agents on quantitative accuracy of PET in combined whole-body PET/MR imaging", *Eur. J. Nucl. Med.*, **39**, 1756 (2012).
- C. Lois et al., "An assessment of the impact of incorporating Time-of-Flight (TOF) into clinical PET/CT imaging", J. Nucl. Med., **51**, 1315 (2010).
- D. J. Kadrmas et al., "Impact of Time-of-Flight on PET Tumor Detection", J. Nucl. Med., 50, 3104 (2009).
- AA. Alves et al. (The LHCb Collaboration), "The LHCb Detector at the LHC", Journal of Instrumentation 3 (2008).